Register of the Okhrana records
Hoover Institution Archives
- XVIII. Revolutionary groups of national minorities of the Russian Empire (Boxes 205-207)
  - a. The Jewish Bund (Boxes 205-206)
    - Expanded conference of the Central and Foreign Committees in Vienna, 1913 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4b)
    - Current political activities of the Bund, 1913 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4c)
    - Circular letter no. 150 of the Amalgamated Workers' "Fereins,", 1913 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4d)
    - Circular letter of the Amalgamated Workers' "Fereins,", 1913 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4e)
    - Geneva conference of the Central Bureau of the Amalgamated Workers' "Fereins,", 1913 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4f)
    - Circular letter no. 152 of the Amalgamated Workers' "Fereins,", 1913 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4g)
    - Bund on the Beilis trial, 1913 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4h)
    - Circular letter no. 155 of the Amalgamated Workers' "Fereins,", 1913 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4i)
    - Revolutionaries in Belgium, 1913 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4j)
    - Ninth Conference of the Amalgamated Organization of Workers' "Fereins" in Geneva, 1914 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4k)
    - Circular letter no. 156 of the Amalgamated Organization of Workers' "Fereins,", 1914 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4l)
    - Conference of United Jewish Unions abroad, 1913 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4m)
    - Circular letter no. 157 of the Amalgamated Organization of Workers' "Fereins" (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4n)
    - Circular letter no. 159 of the Amalgamated Organization of Workers' "Fereins,", 1914 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4o)
    - Bund organizations in Russia, 1914 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4p)
    - Boston conference of the Jewish Socialist Federation, 1914 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4q)
    - Formation of the Jewish-Socialist Agitation Committee in New York, 1914 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4r)
    - Socialist Revolutionary P. Rutenberg sent to America to convene a Jewish congress, 1915 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4s)
    - Geneva Conference of the Bund Foreign Committee, 1915 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4t)
    - Text of a sermon allegedly delivered by a rabbi on the destiny of the Jews, 1916 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4u)
    - Current activities of the Bund, 1916 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4v)
    - Bund Committee Abroad's report at the 2nd International Socialist Congress at Kienthal, 1916 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4w)
    - Bund organizations abroad, 1916 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 4x)
    - Pamphlets, newspaper clippings, agent reports, and mail referring to Bund publications and activities (Index XVIIIa, Folder 5)
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index XVIIIa, Folder 6)
    - Reference: See operational card index file for references to the Bund (Index XVIIIa, Folder 7)
    - Reference: See "Review of Parties Affiliated with the Russian Social Democratic Workers' Party" in XVIb(60, folder 1 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 8)
    - Reference: See intelligence summary no. 8, 1902, on resolutions of the 5th Bund Conference, in XIIIc(2), folder 1 (Index XVIIIa, Folder 9)
  - b. The Zionist movement (Box 206)
    The Zionist movement started in Poland in 1897 and spread rapidly throughout the world. Its prime aim being the awakening of national pride among Jews and its final goal the regaining of Palestine by the Jews, the movement gained the support of wealthy Jews of Western European countries and the United States. The Paris Okhrana surveiled at close quarters the activities of Zionists outside Russia, their meetings, publications, and leaders.
    The documents in Folder 1 include a report on the formation in London of a progressive group called the Zionist-Socialists (1901), which cooperated with the Russian Social Democratic Workers Party; a report on currents existing within the Zionist organization; a report in August 1913 on the formation of the "World Union of Jews," initiated at Frankfurt-am-Main and recruiting members from among wealthy Jews and intellectuals; a report on the Poale Zion Congress in Cracow in October 1913; and a lengthy dispatch to Headquarters in January 1915 informing on Germans seeking contacts with Zionist leaders in Berlin and Cologne, promising the liberation of Jews in Russia and Poland and help for Palestine by a victorious Germany against Jewish cooperation in defeating the Allies; reports on the activities of the Zionists in the international field, especially in the United States; report on the Zionist student organisation Gehaver; and numerous circulars issued by Headquarters.
    Available on microfilm reel 379
    - Dispatches concerning the Zionist movement and its leaders, conferences, Zionist Socialists, Po'alei Zion, Agudos Israel, etc., 1901-1916 (Index XVIIIb, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous papers, circulars, and reports on the Zionist movement, 1897-1915 (Index XVIIIb, Folder 2a)
    - Zionism and the Jewish labor movement, an Okhrana brief for the use of its officers and agents, 1909 (Index XVIIIb, Folder 2b)
    - Basel conference of Zionist delegates from Russia prior to the opening of the 10th Zionist Congress, 1911 (Index XVIIIb, Folder 2c)
    - Report on the 10th Zionist Congress in Basel, 1911 (Index XVIIIb, Folder 2d)
    - Circular report on the 11th Congress in Vienna, 1913 (Index XVIIIb, Folder 2e)
    - Report on the pro-German tendency in Zionism, 1913 (Index XVIIIb, Folder 2f)
    - Circular on the Zionist organization Gehaver, 1915 (Index XVIIIb, Folder 2g)
    - Circular on the All-Russian Zionist Congress in Moscow, 1915 (Index XVIIIb, Folder 2h)
    - Proposed congress of Zionists in New York, 1916 (Index XVIIIb, Folder 2i)
    - Zionist organization Gehaver, 1916 (Index XVIIIb, Folder 2j)
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index XVIIIb, Folder 3)
    - Reference: See the operational card index file for references to Zionist organizations (Index XVIIIb, Folder 4)
  - c. Jewish émigré problems for Russian security abroad (Box 206)
    All Jewish organizations, whether at home or abroad, created problems for the Russian authorities, due to the vast contacts they had with the world's Jewish circles. The pogroms and deportations of Jews and the much publicized Beilis case had caused reaction abroad supported by many Jewish revolutionaries emigrating from Russia. All this was placing the Russian government under constant fire of criticism and demanded a keen vigilance from the Paris Okhrana. The file consists of four folders containing dispatches exchanged between Okhrana Headquarters and the Paris Office, miscellaneous documents, copies of The Worker's Friend and copies of V Pomoshch.
    - Incoming and outgoing dispatches, 1898-1915 (Index XVIIIc, Folder 1)
    - Jewish propaganda pamphlets and statutes of Jewish student associations, 1889-1917 (Index XVIIIc, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper clippings on the Beilis trial (Index XVIIIc, Folder 3)
    - Issues of The Workers' Friend, published in London, and V pomoshch, 1905-1916 (Index XVIIIc, Folder 4)
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index XVIIIc, Folder 5)
    - Reference: See Agent Farce's reports from London, 1902-1906, in VIK, folder 23 (Index XVIIIc, Folder 6)
    - Reference: See booklets and pamphlets in Yiddish, London, 1903, in XVIIr(1) (Index XVIIIc, Folder 7)
  - d. Activities in America: finances for Jewish movements (Box 207)
    Jewish immigrants from Russia, especially those of leftist affiliations, organized the Russian-Jewish Revolutionary Union in New York as early as 1899. They sought both moral and financial support for the similar movement in their former homeland. Bund activities in the United States preceded other Jewish activities, and in April 1914 the Federation of Jewish Socialist Workers, organized by emissaries of the Russian Social Democratic Workers Party, counted 92,000 members.
    Conditions created by World War I permitted the Jewish groups of all political orientations to intensify their activities, and Okhrana agents, supplied detailed information on movements of Jewish leaders and publica- tions and the work of their organizations. Among numerous reports, there are references to money received by two Jewish editors from the Germans for an anti-Russian propaganda campaign (April 1915), plans for the formation of a Jewish Legion for the occupation of Palestine (August 1915) and a congress of American Zionists in Boston (August 1916).
    Available on microfilm reels 379-380
    - Dispatches, notes, and intercepted mail, 1899-1916 (Index XVIIId, Folder 1)
    - Jewish Socialist Labor Federation in New York, 1914 (Index XVIIId, Folder 2a)
    - Agent Bint's report on the foundation of a National Jewish League in New York, 1915 (Index XVIIId, Folder 2b)
    - Philadelphia conference of the Jewish Socialist Federation in America, 1915 (Index XVIIId, Folder 2c)
    - National Workers Conference in New York, 1915 (Index XVIIId, Folder 2d)
    - Bund conference in honor of A. Litvin, 1915 (Index XVIIId, Folder 2e)
    - New York Bund meeting in memory of "Bloody Sunday,", 1915 (Index XVIIId, Folder 2f)
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index XVIIId, Folder 3)
    - Reference: See the operational card index file for references to Jewish organizations in America and Europe (Index XVIIId, Folder 4)
- XIX. Polish revolutionaries (Boxes 207-209)
  The Polish revolutionaries were organized mainly in the Social Democratic Party of the Kingdom of Poland and Lithuania, which cooperated closely with the Russian Social Democratic Workers Party. Until their center of activities was transferred from the Kingdom of Poland to Galicia, the P.S.P. activities were under the surveillance of the Warsaw Okhrana. As the leaders fled abroad (London, 1895), they became targets of the Paris Okhrana.
  Prior to World War I, there were no important centers of Polish revolutionary activities outside of Russian Poland and Austrian Galicia, although Polish delegates attended conventions of the Russian Social Democratic Workers Party abroad. It is the reports on these instances that make the Polish file of the Paris Okhrana. During the war, the activities of Polish leftist and conservative leaders were concentrated in Switzerland.
  This collection is grouped roughly on early insurgents, the revolutionary underground, and leaders. However, no clear-cut separation by topics is possible, and the researcher in any phase of the Polish revolutionary movement may find it necessary to consult all the folders under this index.
  The materials on early Polish revolutionaries are assembled mostly in Folders Nos. 1 to 4, the first one presenting a comprehensive coverage of the Padlewski case (the murder of General Seliverstov), and the subsequent ones on Polish revolutionaries in London and Paris, including much confiscated materials, letters and codes of 1890, and the reports of Polish agents of the Okhrana.
  The documents on Joézef Pilsudski and other important revolutionary leaders are in Folders 5, 6, and 11. More material on the leaders can be culled from Folders 10, 12, and 13, containing dispatches, circulars, and other memoranda on Polish youth activities, student groups revolutionary and terrorist organizations, etc.
  Available on microfilm reels 380-384
  - The Padlewski case (murder of General Seliverstov), 1890-1893 (Index XIX, Folder 1)
    Available on microfilm reel 380
    Includes newspaper clippings and a bound collection of documents concerning the assassin and fellow conspirators.
  - Miscellaneous reports, 1889-1915 (Index XIX, Folder 2)
    Topics include: individuals active in the Polish Socialist Party; Polish émigrés in Paris; Polish revolutionaries in exile; revolutionary codes confiscated from Rapaport's apartment; letters and code in Polish found in Mendelsohn's apartment; notes on Petrova confiscated from Polish revolutionaries; confiscated Reinstein papers; Stepanov's notes; notes and code confiscated at Sawitski's arrest. Also includes a code book.
  - Letters in Polish, 1887-1890 (Index XIX, Folder 3)
    Includes those confiscated from Mendelsohn's apartment.
  - Reports of Polish agents to the Okhrana in Paris, 1892-1910 (Index XIX, Folder 4)
    Reports by Wietrzyk and Bilewicz from London; Malankiewicz (Wierzbicki) and Rzondtza (Gruszewski) from Paris; M. Rakowski ("Polish Azef"); and an anonymous informer.
  - Circulars, dispatches and other materials on Pilsudski and other Polish leaders, 1893-1916 (Index XIX, Folder 5)
    Available on microfilm reel 381
    Includes correspondence of the Grabski brothers in 1893.
  - Dispatches and other notes on Polish leaders concerning their activities and contacts with Russian revolutionaries, 1891-1916 (Index XIX, Folder 6)
  - Intercepted letters forward in dispatches to Headquarters, 1894-1916 (Index XIX, Folder 7)
    Available on microfilm reel 382
  - Dispatches concerning Polish revolutionary and patriotic publications, 1896-1917 (Index XIX, Folder 8)
  - Polish issues in the foreign press: leaflets, clippings and galley proofs (Index XIX, Folder 9)
  - Dispatches and other materials on Polish youth activities, 1914-1916 (Index XIX, Folder 10)
    Subjects include the Union of Polish Progressive Youth; Spojnia; Sokol and Strzelec; Zycie in Lvov; Concordia in Leipzig; the Polish Alliance of Revolutionary Youth; Independent Progressive Youth; Polonia in Munch; the Polish Catholic League; and Polish children in Paris.
  - Activities of Polish leaders in the international field for independent Poland, 1910-1917 (Index XIX, Folder 11)
    Available on microfilm reel 383
    Includes dispatches and circulars relating to political orientation of Polish leaders and their actions in Allied and Central Powers camps.
  - Dispatches on Polish revolutionary organizations and the independence movement, 1894-1916 (Index XIX, Folder 12)
    Available on microfilm reels 383-384
    Includes an 88-page summary prepared by Okhrana Headquarters in 1909.
  - Dispatches and notes on Polish terrorists, anarchists, and socialists, 1894-1917 (Index XIX, Folder 13)
    Available on microfilm reel 384
    Includes materials on contacts between the Polish Socialist Party and the Bund and a copy of Bulletin juif from January 1917.
  - Miscellaneous letters, books, and other materials, 1893-1917 (Index XIX, Folder 14)
    Includes a drawing of a hand grenade, unidentified letters and notes, copy of the Illustrated Polish Weekly from 1915, stamps issued by the Polish Committee for Independence; and an appeal in Russian for support of the Social Democratic Party from 1893. Books include Russisch-polnische Beziehungen (1893), Czego chca? socyaliséci? (1902), Syberya (translation from Kennan); and Listy ulotne. Newspapers include Polonia (no. 10, 1917); Naprzód (nos. 31 and 51, 1904); and Robotnicza Solidarnosc.
  - Cross-reference sheet (Index XIX, Folder 15)
  - Reference: See the operational index file for references to Polish national organizations (Index XIX, Folder 16)
  - Reference: For a review of parties affiliated with the Russian Social Democratic Workers' Party, 1910, see XVIb(6) (Index XIX, Folder 17)
  - Reference: For intelligence summary no. 63, December 11, 1903, for a survey of the Polish socialist movement in Galicia and elsewhere, in XIIIc(2), folder 3 (Index XIX, Folder 18)
  - Reference: For intelligence summary no. 81, December 11, 1904, on activities of the Polish organization Liga Narodowa, see XIIIc(2), folder 4 (Index XIX, Folder 19)
  - Reference: For letters and raw reports from various agents in London in French, Polish, and Russian )and particularly letters on Dembski and others in the 1890s, see XIIIa (Index XIX, Folder 20)
  - Reference: See Agent Farce's reports from London, 1902-1906, in VIk, folder 23 (Index XIX, Folder 21)
- XX. Armenian groups (Box 209)
  The first mention of Armenian activity abroad appears in the Paris Okhrana files in a draft report referring to "Young Armenia," a student organization dating back to 1894 and to the existence of an Armenian Social Democratic group in London. It underlines the characteristic feature of all Armenian organizations, namely their prevailing nationalism, which Russian leftist groups considered untimely and incongruous with the revolutionary cause. The report also gives data on Armenian revolutionary publications ( Gaapara, Gnchak, Mshak, Murcha), Armenian leaders active abroad and their contacts with leftist elements, of Western Europe. Prince Viktor I. Nakashidze, an anarchist, stands out as a strong supporter of the Armenian movement, as do Mikhail Tsereteli, Georgii Dekanozi, Viktor Gogeliani, etc. Agent reports of May 1907 give information on Georgians residing in Switzerland and Paris. Reports from Headquarters send data on one of the most important Armenian organizations -- the Dashnaktsutyun (Dashnakts'ut'iwn) -- and its leaders (November 1907) publications (March 1908), and activities. Other reports in this folder deal with the Droshakists, "Independent Georgia," Armenians in Turkey, the Party of Unity and Progress, the Dashnaktsutyun by countries, including America, Armenian student groups, terrorist plans, etc.
  Folder 2 contains a collection of clippings on Turkish atrocities committed against the Armenians, an Okhrana Headquarters brief on the Caucasian revolutionary movement, a report on the Dashnaktsutyun congress in Constantinople, Armenian revolutionary publications, resolutions adopted by the Armenian Social Democratic Party "Gnchak," the student union of Dashnakists in Paris and Berlin, and the agenda of the Vlllth Dashnaktsutyun congress in Erzerum.
  - a. Organization and newspapers, nationalist and socialist
    Available on microfilm reels 385-386
    - Dispatches pertaining to Armenian revolutionary groups at home and abroad, 1894-1917 (Index XXa, Folder 1)
    - Briefs, reviews, reports and circulars for briefing on Armenian revolutionary groups, 1909-1917 (Index XXa, Folder 2)
      Available on microfilm reel 386
      Includes reports on revolutionary parties in Caucasus (1909); socialists in Georgia (1909); and Dashnak, Gnchak, and other groups in various countries abroad.
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index XXa, Folder 3)
    - Reference: See operational card index file for references to the Dashnaktsutyun Party (Index XXa, Folder 4)
    - Reference: For Agent Kaplun's reports on Georgians in Switzerland, see IIIf, folder 21 (Index XXa, Folder 5)
    - Reference: For Agent Farce's reports from London, 1902-1906, see VIk, folder 23 (Index XXa, Folder 6)
  - b. Intelligence in connection with Tiflis robbery
    The Tiflis robbery, a major, but only one of a series of revolutionary operations, was obviously instigated from abroad by Litvinov, Krasin, and other Leninists, while the attack itself was perpetrated by the local Armenian and Georgian revolutionary terrorists. The first 22 documents in this collection are general or minor reports on this act of "expropriation". The subsequent six reports relate to Litvinov's participation, the arrest of ringleader Kamo in Berlin, and the revolutionary attempts to place in circulation the 500 ruble bank notes from the Tiflis holdup.
    - Dispatches and notes relating to intelligence in connection with the robbery by revolutionaries in Tiflis, 1905-1909 (Index XXb, Folder 1)
    - Reports on Litvinov's party of "expropriators," Kamo's arrest in Berlin, a list of Armenian "expropriators," and revolutionaries marketing stolen 500 ruble bank notes. Also includes clippings from Bulgarian newspapers, 1906-1908 (Index XXb, Folder 2)
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index XXb, Folder 3)
- XXI. Finnish revolutionaries (Box 209)
  In 1899 Headquarters instructed the Paris Office to surveil in London the activity of the "Committee on Finland," presided over by Harold Perrot. From this date on, Finnish matters, especially smuggling arms and clandestine publications to Finland, continued to enter the agenda of the Paris Okhrana. Folder 1 contains a general collection of intelligence dispatches on the subject. The documents in Folder 2 deal with specific subjects: Konni Zilliacus and the northern route for arms smuggling to Finland and Russia, a brief on the political situation in Finland (1909), a circular about German support of the Finnish independence movement, etc.
  - Dispatches pertaining to Finnish revolutionary activities, 1899-1917 (Index XXI, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous dispatches and reports, 1904-1916 (Index XXI, Folder 2)
    Topics include surveillance of Zilliaeus, Finnish agitators, the Northern underground for arms smuggling, a brief on the political situation in Finland, agitation among university youth, and independence movements in Finland supported by Germany.
  - Cross-reference sheet (Index XXI, Folder 3)
  - Reference: See VIIIc for reports on the Finnish movement (1916) (Index XXI, Folder 4)
- XXII. Latvians and Lithuanians (Box 210)
  The main reason in placing Latvian and Lithuanian revolutionary groups in the same file was their regional affiliation. (They are referred to by the Russian authorities as the "Baltic Provinces". ) There are just a few direct references to Lithuanians (and Estonians) in the files of the Paris Okhrana, due to the fact that they did not form a separate national group within the broad scope of the revolutionary movement. While cooperating with the Russian Social Democratic Workers Party, they joined the Poles under the banner of the Social Democratic Party of the Kingdom of Poland and Lithuania. Another reason for the lack of documents referring to Lithuanians in the Paris Okhrana Office was that more prominent Lithuanian leaders were active within the political boundaries of Russia, thus being a target for local Okhrana networks.
  The first mention of an organized Latvian group abroad dates to 1899, when a chapter of their Social Democratic Party was formed in London. From then on the activities of the Latvian Social Democratic Party in Russia had a strong reflection on its exponents abroad living in larger cities of Western Europe. Latvian revolutionaries established a close contact with all national groups cooperating with the Russian Social Democratic Party and kept it up to the outbreak of the October revolution. They attended all important meetings and conventions of the RSDWP, proving themselves as valuable planners and activists for the revolutionary cause. As terrorists, the Latvians made an impressive record. They also smuggled into Russia considerable quantities of clandestine publications and arms during the revolution of 1905.
  Latvian emigres in the United States organized several groups of the Social Democratic Party, but only those active in San Francisco (1911) adhered to the home structure of the Party. Others acted independently. Folder 1 contains the agenda for the 4th Congress of the Latvian Social Democratic Party (March 1913), a trace of financial assistance from the German Social Democrats (July 1913), and evidence that a Latvian Social Democratic group in Boston, Massachusetts, built itself up to a membership of 370.
  War conditions caused a cessation of activities of the Latvian Social Democratic Bureau Abroad, and attempts to revive it in Stockholm failed. Latvian contacts with Lithuanians during World War I became more lively and close. Folder 2 includes documents referring to cooperation between Latvian and Russian anarchists (Lapin and Teplov) for the purpose of smuggling arms to Russia (1909), the political platform of the Latvian Social Democratic Party, an Okhrana chart of the Latvian Social Democratic Party, a summary report on the Lithuanian Social Democratic Party and reports on its conventions, reports on resolutions and the organization of the Bureau of Latvian Social Democratic Groups Abroad, and data on Pietr Brede (Bredis, "Yeshka").
  - Dispatches pertaining to Latvians and Lithuanians in anarchist groups in London, 1899-1916 (Index XXII, Folder 1)
    Available on microfilm reels 386-387
  - Dispatches and agent reports, 1909-1916 (Index XXII, Folder 2)
    Available on microfilm reel 387